A Guide to the Edward B. O'Neal Papers, 1968-1975
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edward B. O'Neal Papers, 1968-1975
The Library of Virginia
41487
7 cubic feet (16 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Portsmouth Public Library.
Biographical Information
Edward Bert O'Neal was born in Rocky Mount, Nash County, North Carolina on 14 July 1925. He was the son of Bert Edward O'Neal (1896-1939) and Clara Eleanor Brown (1905-1971). He attended St. Paul's School in Baltimore, and later moved to Norfolk, Virginia. He served in the U.S. Army during World War II. O'Neal attended the division of the College of William and Mary in Norfolk, where he took a course in business administration, and was employed by an architectural and engineering firm as office manager and bookkeeper. In 1970, O'Neal moved to Atlanta, where he was employed by Atlanta Airport Engineers as an accountant. Edward B. O'Neal died in Norfolk, Virginia on 16 May 1999.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1968-1975, of Edward B. O'Neal (1925-1999) of Norfolk, Virginia, and Atlanta, Georgia, consisting of his genealogical research files on the Cotten/Cotton families of Virginia and North Carolina, specifically the descendants of John Cotton (d. 1728) of Bertie County, North Carolina. O'Neal intended to publish a book entitled Our Southern Heritage: A History of the Cotten/Cotton Families of the South, Their Descendants, and Allied Families. The collection also contains research on the family of Alexander Rankin of Scotland and his descendants, many of whom settled in Tennessee.
There is a substantial amount of information on the allied families of Andrews, Braswell, Brown, Davis, Donelson/Donaldson, Holladay/Holliday, Powell, Rodgers, Turner, Upchurch, Van Tassel, Waugh, and Wilkinson. Areas represented in the collection include Isle of Wight, Nansemond, Princess Anne, Surry, Sussex, and York Counties, Virginia; Betie, Edgecombe, Hertford, and Northampton Counties, North Carolina; and Blount and Knox Counties, Tennesssee.
The papers contain abstracts, transcriptions, and copies of Bible records, census records, deeds, land patents and grants, marriage records, obituaries, pension records, published sources, tombstone inscriptions, and wills. In addition, there is correspondence, family group sheets, and genealogical charts.
Contents List
- Abingdon. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alston. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Andrew. (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
- Armstrong. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- As We Were by Bruce Cotten. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bacon's Rebellion - Anne Cotten (Peter Force's Tracts). (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bagnall (Eley-Braswell-West). (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Balmer. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Banks. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Barnes. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Barrow. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Batte/Batts. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Battle. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Beals/Beale. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Belcher. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bell. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Blair. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Blount. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Braswell. (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Braswell - Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
- Braswell - England (MacLamroc Collection). (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Braswell - Fields, Bill - Correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
- Braswell - Bill Field's Data. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Braswell, Isaac. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Braswell - Isle of Wight County. (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- Braswell - Isle of Wight County - Deeds and Wills. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Braswell, Jacob and Nancy. (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- The Lineage of Jacob Thomas Braswell by Viola Vick Braswell, 1956. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Braswell - Manuscripts. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Braswell - Nash County, NC. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Braswell, Richard. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Braswell, Robert Jr.. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Braswell, William. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Brewer. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Brickell. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Bridger. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Brown. (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Brown, Gen.. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Brown, Samuel Pride. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Buckingham, Eleanor B. - Estate. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Bullock. (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
- Campbell. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Carney. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Carter. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Cartwright. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Cartwright-Keeling-Hobdy-Cotten (Dorothy Louise Milam Julich). (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Carver. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Census Records. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Clark. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Clark, Larry Goodrich. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Coleman. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cook. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Correspondence - Personal. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Correspondence - Registers of Deeds, Clerks, Libraries. (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
- Cotten, Alexander Spotswood. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Cotten, Anna Lee - Christian Ewing Hauer Family. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Cotten, Arthur Kemp. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Cotten, Benjamin (Peggy Gregory's Line). (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Cotten - Bible Records. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Cotten - Cemetery Records. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Cotten - Correspondence. (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
- Cotten - Correspondence - Lines Not Connected. (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
- Cotten - Deeds. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Cotten - Deeds - North Carolina. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Cotten - Family Sketches, etc.. (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
- Cotten - Group Sheets. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Cotten - Heraldry. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Cotten, James. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Cotten, Col. James. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Cotten, Jesse m. Mourning Jones. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Cotten, Joab - Kershaw County (Mrs. Eloise J. Rogers). (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Cotten, John m. Sarah Deason; Cotten, George Washington m. Sarah Elizabeth Wear (Bert Hollis Cotton III). (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Cotten, John = Deeds. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Cotten, Rev. John. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Cotten, Joseph - Halifax County, NC. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Cotten, Lazarus. (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
- Cotten, Lazarus (Leta Baughn). (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Cotten - Marriage Records. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Cotten - Pennsylvania. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Cotten, Samuel. (Box 6, Folder 15-17)
- Cotten, Samuel. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Cotten, Capt. Thomas. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Cotten, Capt. Thomas. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Cotten - Virginia. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Cotten, William m. Sarah (Dew) Bridgers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Cotten, Rev. William. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Cotten - Wills. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Cotten - Wills - North Carolina. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Cotten - Wills - Virginia. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Crawford. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Crocker. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Dalton. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Daniel. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Davis/Davies. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- A History of the Davis Family of "Oakland," NC by Cora Davis Brooks, 1918. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- The Davis Genealogist, 1969. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Sam Davis - Confederate Hero, 1842-1863 by Edythe Johns Rucker Whitley, 1947. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Dawson. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Deloach. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Dew. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Dickinson. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Diggs/Digges/Degge. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Doggett. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Donaldson. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- History of the Donaldson Family, Scotland-America by Mrs. J. Paul Galbraith. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Donelson/Donaldson. (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Duke. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Duncan, John. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Eason. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Edwards. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Erwin/Irwin. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Evans. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Ewell. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Exum. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Feake. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Felton. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Felts. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- A Compilation of the Descendants of William Fenton of County Limerick, Ireland and Petersburg, Virginia by James H. Bailey II. (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Feriby. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Figures. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Flake, Robert Sr. (Isle of Wight County, VA). (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Floyd. (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Fountain. (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Frizzell. (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Galbraith. (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Genealogy of the Cotten Family of North Carolina by Bruce Cotten. (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Gewin. (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
- Godwin. (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Goode. (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Granberry. (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Gray. (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Green. (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Griffin. (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Gwinnett, Button (Charles Francis Jenkins). (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Harrell. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Harriss. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Harvey. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Hassell, C.B.. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Hawkins, Col. Philemon. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Haynes. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Henderson. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Herring. (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Hill. (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
- Hilliard. (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Hobbs. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Hobdy. (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Holladay/Holliday. (Box 9, Folder 14-17)
- Horn. (Box 9, Folder 18)
- House. (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Hudnall. (Box 9, Folder 20)
- The Hudson Family From Prince Edward County, Virginia to Troup County, Georgia by Janie Lovelace Heard, 1969. (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Hunter. (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Huston/Houston. (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Hutchinson, Anne. (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Ivy. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Izzard. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Jeffries/Jefferys. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Jordan. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Josey. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Journal of John Cotten and Its Unreliability. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Keeling. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Keeling - Forsey, Margaret - Correspondence. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Kennon. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Killebrew. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Kinchen. (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Kirven. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Knapp. (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Knight. (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Knox. (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Knox County, TN - Marriage Bonds (A-Q). (Box 10, Folder 16)
- LaMotte. (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Joel Lane: A Pioneer and Patriot of Wake County, North Carolina by Marshall DeLancy Haywood. (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Lanier. (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Lawrence. (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Lee. (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Lewis. (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Lincoln. (Box 10, Folder 23)
- List of Contacts. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Little. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Llewellyn. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Love. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Loveless/Lovelace. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Lovett. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Lowe. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Luttrell. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Mackey. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Makemie. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Martin. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- McCormick. (Box 11, Folder 12)
- McRae. (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Montfort/Mumford. (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Moore. (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Motley. (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Moone (also Green and Davis). (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Mumford. (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Newman. (Box 11, Folder 19)
- Nexsen. (Box 11, Folder 20)
- A Family History of the Family Nexsen and Their Descendants. (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Norfleet. (Box 11, Folder 22)
- Northsworthy. (Box 11, Folder 23)
- North Carolina Estate Papers. (Box 11, Folder 24)
- Oliphant. (Box 11, Folder 25)
- O'Neal - Correspondence. (Box 11, Folder 26)
- Outlaw. (Box 11, Folder 27)
- Pace/Pass. (Box 11, Folder 28)
- Palmer. (Box 11, Folder 29-30)
- Parham. (Box 11, Folder 31)
- Patterson. (Box 11, Folder 32)
- Peebles. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Peele. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Perryman. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Phillips. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Pitt. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Portrait of a Loyalist: James Cotten of Anson County, North Carolina by Robert Martin McBride, 1954. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Princess Anne County, VA Marriage Records. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Powell. (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Powell, William. (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Proctor. (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Pyron (also Drewery and Willoughby). (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Rankin. (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Rankin - Correspondence. (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
- Rankin Relations by A.M. Prichard, 1948. (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Rawls. (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- Revolutionary War Records. (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
- Ricks. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Roane. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Robert-Wood-Mitchell Bible Records. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Rodgers. (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
- Rodgers. (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
- Rodgers - Correspondence. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Commodore John Rodgers by Charles Oscar Paullin, 1910. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Rodgers, Rev. John. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Ruffin. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Rutland. (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Screws. (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Sherrar/Sherrer/Sherrod. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Shipp. (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Shirley. (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Shomo. (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Skinner. (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Slatter. (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Slocum. (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Speight. (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Staton. (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Storm. (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Strange. (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Stringer. (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Sudderth. (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Swann. (Box 14, Folder 22)
- Sweeney. (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Tennent. (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Thigpen. (Box 14, Folder 25)
- Thomas. (Box 14, Folder 26)
- Tooke. (Box 14, Folder 27)
- Toole. (Box 14, Folder 28)
- Turner. (Box 14, Folder 29-30)
- Turner - Tennessee - 1850 Census. (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Turner - Texas. (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Turner - Virginia (Patton Turner, 1965). (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Upchurch. (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
- Urch. (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Van Tassel. (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
- Vick. (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Walton. (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Waugh. (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
- Weeks. (Box 15, Folder 13)
- West. (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Whitehead. (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Whitley. (Box 15, Folder 16-17)
- Wilkinson. (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
- Williams. (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Wilson. (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Winberry. (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Wood. (Box 16, Folder 6)
- The Worthington Family of Florida by Eloise J. Rogers, 1972. (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Wright. (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Young. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Yours Till Death: Civil War Letters of John W. Cotton. (Box 16, Folder 10)